A Guide to the Governor James Barbour Executive Papers, 1812-1814
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Governor James Barbour Executive Papers, 1812-1814
Library of Virginia
41557
7.68 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 5499-5525.
Miscellaneous Reel 5499 - 1812 Jan. 4-Mar. 10
Miscellaneous Reel 5500 - 1812 Mar. 11-April 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5501 - 1812 May 1-31
Miscellaneous Reel 5502 - 1812 June 1-25
Miscellaneous Reel 5503 - 1812 June 26-July 24
Miscellaneous Reel 5504 - 1812 July 25-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5505 - 1812 Sept. 1-Oct. 10
Miscellaneous Reel 5506 - 1812 Oct. 11-Nov. 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5507 - 1812 Dec. 1-31 & Pardons (A-M)
Miscellaneous Reel 5508 - 1812 Pardons (N-W)-1813 Jan. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5509 - 1813 Feb. 1-Mar. 7
Miscellaneous Reel 5510 - 1813 Mar. 8-29
Miscellaneous Reel 5511 - 1813 Mar. 30-Apr. 21
Miscellaneous Reel 5512 - 1813 Apr. 22-May 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5513 - 1813 June 1-30
Miscellaneous Reel 5514 - 1813 July 1-21
Miscellaneous Reel 5515 - 1813 July 22-Aug. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5516 - 1813 Sept. 1-Oct. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5517 - 1813 Nov. 1-Dec. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5518 - 1813 Pardons-1814 Feb. 10
Miscellaneous Reel 5519 - 1814 Feb. 11-Mar. 31
Miscellaneous Reel 5520 - 1814 Apr. 1-May 20
Miscellaneous Reel 5521 - 1814 May 21-June 30
Miscellaneous Reel 5522 - 1814 July 1-Aug. 10
Miscellaneous Reel 5523 - 1814 Aug. 11-Sept. 25
Miscellaneous Reel 5524 - 1814 Sept. 26-Dec. 10
Miscellaneous Reel 5525 - 1814 Undated-Undated
Biographical Information
James Barbour was born in Orange County on 10 June 1775 to Thomas Barbour & Mary Pendleton. Barbour studied law and was admitted to the bar in 1793 in Orange County. He was elected to the House of Delegates in 1798 serving until 1804, and again from 1807 to 1812. Barbour became Speaker of the House of Delegates from December 1809 until January 1812. He was defeated by George William Smith for the governorship in 1811, but was elected to succeed him on 3 January 1812 after Smith's death in the Richmond Theater fire. Barbour served three one-year terms as governor until 11 December 1814. His governorship was defined by his role in defending the Commonwealth from the British during the War of 1812. For nearly two years, Barbour directed a chiefly defensive war against the British paying particular attention to the defense of Norfolk. Barbour maintained close contact with the Secretary of War and militia commanders in filling the various requisitions for militia and making preparations for the defense of the state.
Barbour was elected on 14 November 1814 to the United States Senate for the term commencing 4 March 1815. While in the Senate, Barbour acted as President pro tempore from 1817 to 1820, as well as Chairman of the Committee on Foreign Relations for the Fifteenth, Sixteenth, & Eighteenth Congresses. Barbour served as a senator until 7 March 1825 when he resigned in order to accept an appointment by John Quincy Adams as Secretary of War. Barbour again resigned on 26 May 1828 to become Minister of England until 23 September 1829. Barbour continued to remain active in politics serving as chairman of the 1831 convention of the National Republican Party and 1839 Whig Party convention.
James Barbour married Lucy Maria Johnson on 20 October 1795. The couple had three daughters and four sons including Benjamin Johnson Barbour who served as rector of the University of Virginia. Barbour and his family resided on his Barboursville estate in Orange County which was designed by Thomas Jefferson and built by Barbour in 1817. Barbour died of prostate cancer on 7 January 1842 and is buried in the family cemetery.
Scope and Content
James Barbour's Executive papers primarily consist of incoming correspondence during his three one-year terms as governor from 4 January 1812 to 11 December 1814. These papers are arranged chronologically with pardons arranged to the rear. The correspondence in this collection relates to a variety of topics, however, the most significant correspondence during Barbour's governorship relates to the defense of Virginia from the British during the War of 1812. Other correspondence includes appointments & recommendations for state positions; prisoners & the Virginia Penitentiary; arms & the Virginia Manufactory of Arms; Fort Powhatan; the Powder Magazine at Westham; the Public Guard; the militia; resignations; state expenses & revenue; and others. In addition to correspondence, there are resolutions from the Virginia Senate & House of Delegates; accounts; oaths; muster rolls; pay rolls; pardons; proposals; receipts; election returns; certificates; qualifications; petitions; reports; appointments; resignations; bonds; commissions; orders; proceedings; applications; and other sundry items.
The Governor received correspondence from three main sources: the Federal government, Virginia State government, and Governors from other states. Federal government correspondents include President James Madison; James Monroe, Secretary of State; William Eustis, John Armstrong, & James Monroe, Secretaries of War; and William B. Giles & John W. Eppes, Virginia's representatives in the Senate. President James Madison writes on 26 February 1814 regarding the appointment of an engineer to make a further examination & report with respect to Fort Powhatan. James Monroe, as Secretary of State, writes Governor Barbour enclosing the act of Congress declaring war on Great Britain & Ireland (enclosure not included - See Executive Communications) (1812 June 19). On 1 July 1812, Monroe encloses an act of Congress "to ascertain the western boundary of the tract reserved for satisfying the military bounties allowed to the officers and soldiers of the Virginia Line on Continental Establishment." Later, Monroe writes in support of the memorial of the daughters of Col. Robert H. Harrison, aid-de-camp to General Washington during the Revolutionary War (1812 Nov. 23). In his letter dated 21 March 1813, Monroe discusses the raising of a regiment for the defense of Norfolk & the neighboring coast and the mediation between the United States & Great Britain offered by Russia. In addition, Monroe writes regarding the claim of the Virginia State Line for an equal portion of the bounty land with those who served on Continental Establishment. In this same letter, Monroe remarks on the crimes committed by British troops at Hampton (1813 Oct. 23). Lastly, Monroe submits copies of the laws passed during the late session of Congress on the subject of the militia (1814 May 2).
The majority of correspondence from the Federal government, however, originates from the War Department. William Eustis writes regarding the President's call for the various executives to organize, arm, & equip their proportion of one hundred thousand militia (1812 April 15). Eustis writes again on 30 April 1812 regarding the calling out of the militia and measures for the defense of Norfolk. His letter of 27 May 1812 too relates to the defense of Norfolk. On 18 July 1812, Eustis requests two companies of artillery & five hundred infantry to Norfolk. On 1 September 1812, Eustis writes regarding the President's request for Virginia to call out, arm, & equip fifteen hundred of the detached militia to cooperate with the Northwestern Army. Lastly, Eustis writes regarding a commission for deputy quartermaster (1812 Sept. 7). Eustis was temporarily succeeded by James Monroe, Secretary of State. Monroe writes regarding the protection of the seaport towns (1813 Feb. 3).
John Armstrong, Jr., was appointed Secretary of War on 5 February 1813. Armstrong writes regarding orders to Col. Constant Freeman to concentrate the new recruits at Norfolk (1813 Feb. 10). On 22 March 1813, Armstrong writes regarding the enemy force and his authorization to Gen. Robert B. Taylor to make a further requisition for additional militia if necessary. Later, he encloses a letter from Col. J. Swift, Chief Engineer, informing him on the insignificance of Fort Powhatan against an exterior enemy (1813 Oct. 20). Additional correspondence from Armstrong relates to the following topics: the recall of three or four companies provided they are supplied under the second requisitions (1813 April 11); the law appointing an officer denominated as Paymaster of the Army (1813 April 27); the approval of Brig. Gen. Robert B. Taylor's measures (1813 July 3); the lack of rifles for distribution to the militia (1813 Aug. 4); the assignment of Big. Gen. Moses Porter to Norfolk (1814 April 2); a request that Gen. William B. Chamberlayne remain in command at Norfolk for several weeks until the arrival of Brig. Gen. Moses Porter (1814 April 8); the need for a brigadier general as part of the requisitions for militia (1814 April 18); the report of Decius Wadsworth regarding the construction of blockhouses at Fort Powhatan (1814 April 25); the quota of the requisition by the United States on Virginia (1814 July 4); the disposition of two thousand militia from the requisition on Virginia (1814 July 18); a detachment of militia referred to in the Governor's letter (1814 July 22); and the refusal by the commanding officer of the 8th Virginia Brigade to be called into service by Brig. Gen. Moses Porter at Norfolk (1814 Aug. 20). Armstrong was forced to resign as Secretary of War on 4 September 1814 following the burning of the Capitol.
James Monroe replaced Armstrong as Secretary of War. Monroe writes on 31 August 1814 regarding the enemy's evacuation of Nottingham. On 1 September 1814, Monroe writes regarding the embarkation of the enemy vessels on the Patuxent and the danger of other principal towns including Richmond, Norfolk, & Baltimore (1814 Sept. 1). Shortly thereafter, Monroe writes of the inability to prevent the enemy from passing the battery at the White House on the Potomac River, the departure of the fleet down the Patuxent River, and the possibility of an attack on Richmond or Norfolk (1814 Sept. 6). The same day he writes the Governor again regarding a request to the Governor of North Carolina for fifteen hundred troops to report to the commanding officer at Norfolk. On 14 September 1814, he writes of the unsuccessful attempt by the British to capture Baltimore by land & water. Monroe encloses a letter he received from Maj. Gen. S. Smith communicating this intelligence. Additional correspondence from Monroe includes the following subjects: the movements of the enemy past Annapolis and the defense of Norfolk & Richmond (1814 Sept. 19); additional requisitions for militia to march for Washington (1814 Oct. 2); the expense attending the militia called into service (1814 Oct. 6); the order of Gen. Joel Leftwich's Brigade & John Breckinridge's Brigade to Washington (1814 Oct. 15) Lt. Col. Hamilton's orders to proceed to the Northern Neck with five hundred men of the 3rd Rifle Regiment (1814 Nov. 3); and muskets, rifles, & heavy ordnance for the ensuing year from the Armory at Virginia (1814 Nov. 18).
Virginia's representatives in Congress correspond occasionally with Governor Barbour. William B. Giles, Virginia's senator in Congress, writes regarding the resolutions of the General Assembly respecting the right of the several state legislatures to instruct its senators in Congress (1812 Nov. 30). Giles again writes on 20 November 1813 regarding the adjusting of the account between the U. S. and the individual states for expenses incurred in calling forth the militia. Giles also encloses an act to provide for calling forth the militia to execute the laws of the Union. On 17 July 1813, John W. Eppes writes requesting information on the conduct of the enemy at Hampton for a committee of the House of Representatives. In addition, Eppes informs the Governor of the location of the enemy fleet on the Potomac River seventy miles below Alexandria. Eppes also writes concerning a revision of the militia laws and the expenses of the state during the war (1813 Dec. 23). Lastly, Eppes encloses a letter from Hugh Nelson, U. S. House of Representatives, regarding Virginia's claim for supplies against the U. S. (1814 Jan. 1). Similarly, in a letter dated 8 April 1814, Virginia's delegation in Congress writes regarding Virginia's claim against the U. S. for the reimbursement of money expended by the state in calling out, equipping, & marching its militia.
The majority of correspondence in James Barbour's Executive Papers originates from Virginia State government. Significant correspondents from Virginia State government include key military figures during the War of 1812 such as Brig. Gen. Robert B. Taylor, Aid-de-Camp John Myers, Brig. Gen. Moses Porter, Lt. Col. William Sharp, William Lambert, James Bankhead, and Deputy Adjutant Generals William W. Hening & Claiborne W. Gooch. Additionally, prominent correspondents within Virginia State government include John Staples, Superintendent of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms; Peter Crutchfield, Commandant of the Public Guard; Abraham Douglas & William Campbell, Keepers of the Penitentiary; Philip N. Nicholas, Attorney General; William Munford, Clerk of the House of Delegates; Theodosius Hansford, Clerk of the Senate; and Samuel Shepard & John Burfoot, Auditors of Public Accounts.
Brigadier General Robert B. Taylor corresponded frequently with Governor Barbour regarding topics of a military nature. Taylor accepted a commission as lieutenant colonel of the 3rd Regiment of Virginia Cavalry on 27 April 1812. More importantly, Taylor writes the Governor on 14 January 1813 accepting the office of brigadier general in charge of the defense of Norfolk. Taylor was placed under Federal authority on 9 February 1813 commanding the 5th Military District. Taylor mostly provides the Governor with intelligence on the strength of the enemy forces, its movements, & location (1813 March 10, 11, 13, 16, 18, 28, & 29; & 1813 April 1). Taylor also corresponds with respect to the following subjects: Col. Armistead of the Engineer Corps, exemptions for Quakers, pay for soldiers, & the deficiency of officers (1813 March 21); the increase in the enemy's forces in Lynhaven Bay with the arrival of Admiral Warren, attacks on vessels near Craney Island & the Nansemond River and the advance of barges "up the roads" (1813 March 24); a request that the artillery at Gloucester and other companies not be dismissed, payment to the troops, tents, & powder (1813 March 26); an extract of the general orders of the War Department on the proportions of officers, non-commissioned officers, & privates (1813 March 26); the arrival of General Wade Hampton, payment of troops, & uniforms (1813 April 27); his plan to uniform the militia (1813 April 29); the cost of horses, the transfer of Capt. Green's Company to Fredericksburg with Capt. Benedict, & the discharge of Capt. Taylor's Company from Petersburg (1813 May 19); sickness, desertions, & enemy movements (1813 June 19); drafts on the neighboring counties & the strength of the enemy forces (1813 June 27); the defense of Nansemond (1813 July 2); the possible intention of the enemy & the need for camp equipage, accoutrements, & wagons (1813 July 1); the replacement of troops whose term of service will soon expire (1813 July 15); his trips to Richmond & Washington to meet with the Secretary of War (1813 July 16); his awaiting the orders of the Secretary of War in Georgetown (1813 July 25); the arrival of troops from Holly Spring Camp & payment for their freight (1813 Aug. 20); the claim of Virginia for rations & pay (1813 Oct. 3); Capt. Sandford's application for 3rd lieutenant (1813 Oct. 31); the situation of the troops at Hampton (1813 Nov. 5); and a requisition for militia to be placed in the service of the U. S. & organized into companies of cavalry, artillery, riflemen, & infantry (1813 Dec. 13).
John Myers, aid-de-camp, too writes regarding the enemy movements in the absence of Brig. Gen. Taylor. On 30 March 1813, Myers informs the Governor of the position of the enemy fleet, as well as the position of the U. S. S. Constellation at Craney Island. Myers later relates the capture of British sailors who were taken on board the U. S. S. Constitution (1813 April 13). On 17 June 1813, Myers encloses a letter from Maj. William Nimmo, 1st Bn. 2nd Virginia Regt., regarding the demand of the British Frigate Atalante for sheep & oxen with a threat of force. Finally, there is a letter from Myers regarding enemy movements and two British deserters (1813 July 12).
Moses Porter was promoted to Brevet Brigadier General on 10 September 1813. On 1 November 1814, Brigadier General Moses Porter succeeded Brig. Gen. Thomas Parker, who had replaced Taylor on 5 February 1814. Porter writes regarding the defenseless situation at Norfolk and suggests organizing a provisional force of two thousand men to be equipped by the state (1814 July 4). On 15 July 1814, Porter requests that the militia in the vicinity of Norfolk be excluded from the draft for an additional force. Later, he requests an additional company or two of the local militia to be stationed at Fort Powhatan (1814 July 19). In August 1814, Porter notifies the Governor of the arrival of twenty-three additional sail up the Chesapeake (1814 Aug. 16) and comments on the inadequate force at Fort Powhatan (1814 August 30).
Lt. Col. William Sharp, as commander of the 54th Regiment of Virginia Militia at Norfolk Borough, played an important role in the defense of Norfolk against the British. Sharp communicated with Governor Barbour throughout the war, but his correspondence was particularly valuable before the arrival of Brig. Gen. Taylor. Significant correspondence from Lt. Col. Sharp includes the following: the death of Brig. Gen. Thomas Mathews (1812 Feb. 24); the defenseless situation of Norfolk & the condition of arms & ammunition (1812 April 12); arms at Norfolk & the establishment of a general deposit of arms (1812 April 18); arms & ammunition for his regiment (1812 June 29); the appearance of a British Squadron of ships in Lynhaven Bay (1813 Feb. 4); a letter from William C. Veale regarding a boatload of prisoners sent onshore from the British Squadron (1813 Feb. 6); a mob of Spanish & Portuguese sailors who assembled at Norfolk & the firing of heavy cannon near Craney Island & Fort Norfolk (1813 Feb. 8).
William Lambert was appointed an agent stationed at Windmill Point in Lancaster County, at the mouth of the Rappahannock River, to watch & report on enemy movements. Lambert's correspondence details depredations of the enemy in Northumberland County (1814 March 25); the force of the enemy at New Point (1814 April 1); enemy movements up the Chesapeake & runaway slaves taken by the enemy (1814 April 8); enemy movements up the Rappahannock River (1813 April 22); enemy depredations on the Corotoman Estate (1814 April 29); the taking of slaves by the enemy in Northumberland County (1814 May 8); an attempt by the enemy to land on the southern shore of the Potomac for the purpose of taking slaves (1814 May 13); enemy movements up the Chesapeake & a landing of three thousand British troops in the Northern Neck (1814 July 22); enemy movements on the Rappahannock River & the destruction of property by British troops in Westmoreland County (1814 July 29); and enemy depredations at Kinsale & the capture of three schooners on Cone Creek (1814 Aug. 12).
James Bankhead served as Assistant Adjutant General to the Adjutant General of Virginia at Norfolk. In this capacity, Bankhead writes regarding the exposed situation of Norfolk on 12 April 1814. In this letter, Bankhead also encloses a report of state property at Norfolk. On 10 August 1814, he encloses the requisition on the Executive of Virginia for a regiment of militia. His letter of 24 November 1814 comments on the strength of the post at Norfolk. Finally, on 2 December 1814, Bankhead reports that Admiral Cockburn's Squadron is on the Rappahannock with a determination to plunder the inhabitants & devastate the country. Bankhead also mentions the arrival of troops at Bermuda with New Orleans as their supposed destination.
William W. Hening & Claiborne W. Gooch served as Deputy Adjutant Generals under Adjutant General Moses Green during the War of 1812. Hening writes concerning the strength of the 15th & 59th Regiments (1812 Feb. 9); the overall strength of the militia (1812 March 28); extra compensation for his new duties as Deputy Adjutant General during the war (1812 July 3); a regulation to keep the requisition full (1813 Feb. 13); a recommendation by the Frederick County Court for Henry St. George Tucker as captain of a troop of cavalry (1813 July 14); and the procurement of horses (1814 Sept. 22). On several occasions, Claiborne Gooch submitted general orders for Moses Green calling out the militia to Norfolk to replace those whose term of service will expire (1814 Feb. 17; 1814 March 31; 1814 May 8 & 13; & 1814 June 29). In addition, Gooch provides general orders regarding the inspection of arms, accoutrements, ammunition, etc., in preparation for invasion (1814 June 22); the requisition of the President on the militia of Virginia (1814 July 20); and the requisition of the commanding General at Norfolk (1814 Aug. 13).
John Staples, as Superintendent of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms, corresponded frequently with the Governor regarding arms and the Manufactory in Richmond, Virginia. Staples encloses monthly statements of the operations of the Manufactory from January 1812 to November 1814. Some of these statements were prepared by Stephen Woodson, Clerk. In addition, Staples also corresponds respecting the following topics: musket stocks from Philadelphia (1812 Jan. 8); recommendations in favor of Stephen Woodson as clerk of the Virginia Manufactory of Arms (1812 Feb. 10); the number of arms on hand & the number of arms issued since 21 December 1811 (1812 Feb. 27); the roof of the Armory (1812 March 6); the number of cannon on hand (1812 April 3); a burst gun manufactured at the Virginia Manufactory (1812 Aug. 31); a list of unmounted cannon for service, not fit for service, old cannon shot, new cannon shot, & arms (1813 Jan. 6); instructions as to the propriety of the corps under his command to perform sentinel duty at the Armory (1813 Feb. 6); the Foundry and manufacture of cannon for the United States and other states (1813 March 1); artificers to accompany troops for the purpose of repairing arms (1813 April 10); the building of a powder magazine at Westham (1813 June 24); pistols & scabbards for cavalry swords (1813 Sept. 6); a vacancy in the office of Assistant Armorer due to the resignation of George Edington (1813 Sept. 30); the organization of the artificers into a select company (1813 Dec. 3); salt on the coast of Princess Anne County (1814 Jan. 27); new rifles requiring repairs (1814 Feb. 3); defective rifles manufactured by Frederick Sheets (1814 Feb. 3); waste water below the Manufactory (1814 Feb. 14); old cartouche boxes (1814 Feb. 22); and accounts for repairing arms (1814 Nov. 10). Also noteworthy is a report by Staples & William Campbell estimating the cost of a powder magazine at Westham (1813 June 16).
Peter Crutchfield, Commandant of the Public Guard, provides monthly returns of arms & accoutrements belonging to the Public Guard, monthly reports of the daily duties performed by the Public Guard, and monthly muster rolls from January 1812 to November 1814.